<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Your Best Friends Wants the Freest Rolexes - RPG</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/rpg.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2022-02-23T12:22:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Intro to Fantasy Heartbreaker</title><link href="/intro-to-fantasy-heartbreaker.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-23T12:22:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-23T12:22:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Freest Rolexes</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-02-23:/intro-to-fantasy-heartbreaker.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After reading OSR blogs on and off and collecting weird adventures and systems since circa 2013, I &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; decided to dip my toe into actually playing a little over a year ago.  I had played D&amp;amp;D 2nd edition in my younger days, but the long gap made me nervous …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After reading OSR blogs on and off and collecting weird adventures and systems since circa 2013, I &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; decided to dip my toe into actually playing a little over a year ago.  I had played D&amp;amp;D 2nd edition in my younger days, but the long gap made me nervous to DM a style of gameplay that was similar, but still different than what I had played before. I finally pulled the trigger with a small group, running B2: Keep on the Borderlands using the Black Hack 2e (TBH2e).  I had long admired TBH, and thought it would be fun to run the first adventure I ever played (my old DM ran a lot of B/X, AD&amp;amp;D 1e adventures well into 2e's reign).  Anyway, the game was fun!  The group slowly started growing and after a few side-quests the group finally defeated the vile cultists of Ragborh, god of pestilence and famine, in the Caves of Chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was right around this time, though, that I started noticing some warts on TBH.  Some of the characters had made it to 3rd level, while a few new characters were gifted with especially high stats, and all of a sudden I had a super-powered army that was steamrolling any encounter I put in front of them.  I started beefing up the monster stats, increasing the number of monsters, whatever I thought would make the encounters less of a cake-walk.  None of those ideas helped much.  The worst moment was when the party of six decided they should wade into battle with 40 skeletons, four of which spewed fire.  The party won the battle with only a single character death, but it took forever to play out and was ultimately pretty boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other things I could do (of course) to present challenges: attack the full character sheet vs just hit points, sprinkle in more traps or special rooms, provide more speedbumps to the exploration/encumbrance aspect of the game, etc.  But I still needed combat to be a challenge, something that the characters were affraid of, because it was impacting other aspects of old-school play. Why try to negotiate with or trick a faction if you can kill them all without much risk?  Why sneak or come up with crazy attack plans when a direct assault is fine?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why are you like this, the Black Hack?  Why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I discuss why I think this happened, I'll quickly lay out the combat mechanics of TBH.  The primary mechanic of TBH is a roll-under-stat system - meaning that the result of a 1d20 roll is a success if it is below the target stat.  This mechanic applies directly to combat, via both attack and defense rolls. The only way a monster impacts the outcome of a combat, then, is by dealing damage when a player fails their defense roll and the &lt;em&gt;Powerful Foe&lt;/em&gt; rule.  The &lt;em&gt;Powerful Foe&lt;/em&gt; rule says that when a monster's hit dice number is higher than the player's level, add the difference of the Hit Dice and Level to attack and defense rolls. So a big difference between between monster and character power level will lead to worse results for the player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most other aspects of combat are similar to B/X D&amp;amp;D: hit points, weapon damage ranges, class specific damage dice, etc.  There are two apsects of a typical combat, though, that are very different than B/X: the Warrior class's &lt;em&gt;Dealer of Death&lt;/em&gt; ability and armor.  Armor has a number of "blocks" that a player can use to reduce all damage from an attack; these blocks can be regained via resting.  &lt;em&gt;Dealer of Death&lt;/em&gt; is a pile of d6s that the Warrior can split up between multiple attacks, where each die is rolled for damage on a successful attack.  Warriors start out with a single die and gain a new die for each level.  &lt;em&gt;Dealer of Death&lt;/em&gt; is useable for every attack with no limits.  No other character class has increasing damage die or multiple attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suspicions for I was having trouble challenging my players in combat encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High stats in combat are very, &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; strong. A 17 in STR, the stat tested for melee combat, would result in an 80% success rate atacking and defending.  At first level, that 17 STR character is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; stronger than an 17 STR fighter in B/X&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Powerful Foe&lt;/em&gt; will reduce those odds, but getting to 55% (a 17 STR 1st level B/X fighter attacking an Orc) requires a 6 HD monster, which is crazy for a 1st level combat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a &lt;em&gt;Powerful Foe&lt;/em&gt; actually hits the character, the character can use armor to block all damage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A high-level Warrior can deal a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of damage via &lt;em&gt;Dealer of Death&lt;/em&gt; and monster attack damage and hit points don't scale at nearly the same rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An obvious fix to this is to reduce the range of possible values for stats - like 4d4 (4-16) instead of 3d6 (3-18).  And it works!  I'm running another adventure with this group of players, but different characters rolled up using 4d4.  These characters seem more like 1st level characters in the system, but my players have told me multiple times that they don't like that each character seems so "generic".  I think this view is based on expectations from other editions of D&amp;amp;D, since specific stat values are more impactful in TBH than B/X, which has far less granularity.  The total spread on the 5 characters rolled up is 8-12, which, to the players' point, does seem kind of generic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apologize for this lengthy dissection of the TBH rules, but I needed to get this out of my head and onto "paper" so I could move on to discussing my main point: why I'm coming up with my own ruleset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Players, who needs 'em?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to disliking my 4d4 idea for stats, my players had other complaints about the game.  The spellcasters wanted more diversity in their spells. The thief was discouraged at the lack of mechanical updates or choices at level up.  The fighters seemed pretty pleased with things (though they wouldn't mind more magical weapons).  I suggested that the characters could spend time in cities doing research or canvasing low-lives for info to get their spells/abilities/magic items, but because it wasn't integrated into the rules, the players didn't seem to remember it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this was all happening I was reading a bunch of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship_of_Theseus"&gt;Ship of Theseus&lt;/a&gt; fantasy adventure RPG rulesets (a term I cribbed from &lt;a href="https://www.prismaticwasteland.com/"&gt;Prismatic Wasteland&lt;/a&gt; - maybe on a Discord?).  These are rulesets that have replaced so many mechanics from D&amp;amp;D that they don't resemble the original rules, but still plays a lot like classic D&amp;amp;D. In these systems, I found mechanics that could be solutions to my problems as well as some other really neat ideas I wanted to play with.  The games in question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://errantrpg.carrd.co/"&gt;Errant&lt;/a&gt; - this system is so great. I could see using this wholeclotch, but I was worried that the character classes and experience system pushed too much onto the players.  Some of my players would relish it, others would be put off (I think).  My rules are likely to be a thinly veneered Errant (it really is great - I can't wait for the physical copies to be sent out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/373288/Neoclassical-Geek-Revival-Acidic-2nd-Edition?src=newest"&gt;Neoclassicl Geek Revival&lt;/a&gt; - there are &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; many interesting ideas in this game, but I think its more mechnical challenging to learn than my group is interested in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/348791/Worlds-Without-Number"&gt;Worlds Without Number&lt;/a&gt; - a very granular character creation system with a good skill system (and an amazing set of procedures for building environments, adventures, characters, ...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gruszczy.itch.io/modern-adventuring-plunder"&gt;Modern Adventuring &amp;amp; Plunder&lt;/a&gt; - a classless, level-less system that had implemented a lot of vague ideas I was kicking around in my head.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all came together to make me think maybe I should make my own ruleset that made both me and my players happy.  I think it's possible?  Worst case, we just keep tweaking TBH until we've Ship of Theseus'd it. :wink:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fantasy Heartbreaker Design Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System is compatible with B/X, OSR, AD&amp;amp;D 1e modules&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have simple guidelines for converting rules on the fly when necessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combat should be quick, deadly, and interesting&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tactical decisions, some randomness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce multiple initiative rounds of "hit it with my sword" actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast character generation and jump-right-in complexity&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complexity can increase with levels, but new characters should be easy to "grok"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New characters should be able to contribute to adventures with long-lived characters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide mechanical choices to characters upon advancement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incorporate player-driven quests and world building into the mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future I plan to work through these goals and see if I can make a game system that works for me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="RPG"></category><category term="Fantasy Heartbreaker"></category><category term="B2"></category><category term="TBH2e"></category></entry></feed>